你得發誓
I need your oath.
新礦石的第一絲蹤跡
The first traces of a new ore.
埃爾隆德保證 吉爾加拉德派他來這里并沒有惡意
Elrond has been very convincing in his assurances
埃爾隆德的話讓人非常信服
that Gil-galad bore no ill intent when he sent him here.
感覺事有蹊蹺
There is something more at work.
去林頓吧
Go to Lindon.
看看是怎么回事
Find out what.
你被踢出海上衛隊了  你們仨全部淘汰
You're off the Sea Guard! All three of you!
夠了
Enough!
我毀了朋友們的生活 羞辱了家門
I just ruined my friends' lives, shamed our family name.
你去找那些在舊瞭望塔避難的人
Go to the Men who have taken refuge in the old watchtower.
給他們捎個口信
Deliver to them a message.
你的人民要想保全性命 必須放棄這些土地的所有權
That your people may live if you forsake all claim to these lands
并向他宣誓效忠
and swear fealty to him.
總有一天 我們真正的國王會歸來
One day, our true king will return.
我相信你關在地牢里的那一位
I believe the man you hold in your dungeons
是流亡在外 下落不明的南方大地王位繼承人
is the lost heir in exile to the throne of the Southlands.
我請求您與我并肩作戰
I call on you to fight with me...
-我愿意出征  -我愿意出征
-I will serve! -I will serve!
避免索隆將他們的土地據為己有
...before Sauron claims their lands for his own.
你撒謊
You have lied,
還把危險的外族人帶了進來
brought a dangerous outsider into our midst.
我們要掉隊了
We're going to be left behind.
這就是我們大家不會掉隊的原因
This is how we keep up with the others.
因為他會幫我們 我們也會幫他
He helps us, and... and we help him.
指環王：力量之戒
第一季第五集
本WEB版外掛字幕由  風吹來的那片云  雙語合并
“千禧”
My great thumb. My great thumb.
不對 應該念遷…遷徙
No. Mi... Migration.
遷-徙
Like, mi-gra-tion.
意思就是搬家 我們毛腳族搬家就叫做遷徙
Means, like, to move. What we do, Harfoots.
是這樣 我們會去老林子過冬
You see, we... we winter in Old Forest,
仲夏時節 我們會 趁蝸牛鮮美時前往諾菲德山谷捕食
and mid-summer, we make for Norfield Glen to snail while the snailing's good.
-“蝸牛”  -沒錯 蝸牛
-"Snails, snails"? -Snails, yeah.
在橡樹葉剛剛開始變紅的秋天 我們前往格羅夫果園
And at the first blush of the oak leaves, we head to the Grove.
整個果園
A whole orchard,
到處都是蘋果 李子 杏子 胡蘿卜 你肯定很喜歡
popping with bar apples, plums, apricots, carrots, you'll... you'll love it.
當然了 唯一的麻煩是 從一地遷徙到另一地要歷經重重危險
Of course, the only trouble is there's a hundred perils between here and there.
“危險”
"Perils"?
就是威脅
Like a danger.
比如人類 狼群 霧 雨
You know, big folk, wolves, fog, rain,
山嶺食人妖 洞穴食人妖 只要能殺死你的都算是威脅
hill-trolls, cave-trolls, anything that'll kill ya.
“殺死”
"Kill"?
意思就是把某個東西弄死掉
Means to make somethin' dead.
那我就是個危險
I'm peril.
不 你不是的
No. No, no, you're not.
-更像是說… -不 螢火蟲
-It's more... -No. Fireflies.
那是一次意外 就是…
-That was just an accident. It's...
你不是危險
You're not a peril.
你很好
You're good.
我很好
I'm good?
你很好 因為你是來幫忙的
You're good. Because you're here to help.
諾瑞
Nori!
好了 其他人現在應該準備好了
Oh, great. Others should be ready by now.
小腿跑起來
Quick sticks!
我們走 來啊
Let's go. Come on.
我…
I... I'm...
我很好
I'm good.
你再敢用那根拐杖戳我
Poke me with that crutch again,
我就趁你睡覺的時候 拔掉你腳趾上的毛發
I'll pluck the hair off your toes in your sleep.
那你拔毛的時候 順便把我的耳朵也揪掉吧
And I'll pluck off my ears while you're at it.
省得我再聽你的鼾聲
It'd save me listenin' to your snorin'.
閉嘴吧 我才不打呼嚕呢
Oh, stuff. I do not snore.
-你確實打呼嚕 -你確實打呼嚕
-Yes, you do.
快走吧 動起來 不邁腿永遠都去不了格羅夫
Come on, now. Grove's not gonna migrate to us.
你要是給我們唱你媽媽的趕路歌 沒準能幫我們走快點
Might help us move faster if you sang us your mam's walking song.
是啊 唱吧 波比 喊兩嗓子
Yeah, go on, Pops, give us a warble.
唱吧 能給我們趕路加油鼓勁
Oh, come on, it'll do us some good.
太陽正在落下
-The sun is fast fallin'
落在森巖的樹林后方
Beneath trees of stone
塔中之光
The light in the tower
不再是家鄉
No longer my home
過去燈火朦朧
Past eyes of pale fire
黑沙做我的睡床
Black sand for my bed
我用所知的一切
I trade all I've known
換取未知的未來
For the unknown ahead
呼喚我 遙遠之地 請呼喚我
Call to me Call to me lands far away
羅瓦尼安之丘-韋德布魯克
因為我現在 必須在這流浪的日子里游蕩
For I must now wander this wandering day
副崖-灰色沼澤
我必須游蕩
Away I must wander
在這流浪的日子里
This wandering day
我缺水
Of drink I have little
我少食
And food I have less
我的力量告訴我不行 但是這條路要求我踏足
My strength tells me no But the path demands yes
鮭鱒彎
我雙腿很短 而道阻且長
My legs are so short And the way is so long
無法休息 何談舒適
I've no rest nor comfort
無所慰藉 唯有歌聲
No comfort, but song
西斯爾戴爾-辮子
為我歌唱 遙遠之地 請為我歌唱
Sing to me, sing to me Lands far away
請起身指引我度過這流浪的日子
Oh, rise up and guide me This wandering day
請答應要找到我
Please promise to find me
在這個流浪的日子
-This wandering day
最終 他們的答案來了
-At last comes their answer
穿過寒冷和霜凍
Through cold and through frost
并非所有的流浪者都身陷迷途
That not all who wonder or wander are lost
不論悲傷
No matter the sorrow
不計成本
No matter the cost
并非所有的流浪者都身陷迷途
That not all who wonder Or wander are... Lost
隧道挖通了 大人
The tunnel is complete, my lord.
給我看看你的手臂
Your arm. Show it to me.
感覺怎么樣
How does it feel?
像被火烤一樣疼 父親大人
Like fire, Lord-father.
我真希望你能像我一樣感受陽光
I wish you could feel it like I do.
因為太陽很快就要消失了
For soon, it will be gone.
我身體里能感受到溫暖的那部分 也將隨之消失
And with it, the part of me that knew its warmth as well.
我會想念它的
I shall miss it.
是時候了 去召集軍團吧
Summon the legions. It is time.
我們的敵人揚言要發起進攻
-Our enemy vows to attack.
要想活命
In exchange for mercy,
敵人命令我們放棄這座瞭望塔
we've been ordered to abandon this tower
并向他們的指揮官宣誓效忠
and swear fealty to their commander.
我明白我不是 你們翹首以盼的那個國王
I know I'm not the king you have awaited.
但如果你們選擇和我并肩戰斗
But if you choose to stand with me and fight,
那這座瞭望塔 將不再會是我們脆弱的招牌
this tower will no longer be a reminder of our frailty,
而將會變成我們力量的象征
but a symbol of our strength.
有誰愿意和我并肩作戰
Who will stand with me?
你們當中有誰愿意奮起作戰
Who among you will stand and fight?
-好的 我們戰斗吧 -好的
-Aye, let's do it. -Aye.
奮起作戰
Stand and fight?
你們會死的
You will die.
要我說 我們最好碰碰運氣
I say it'd be better to take our chances
臣服于所謂的敵人
bowing to the supposed enemy.
我直視過敵人的眼睛
I have looked that enemy in the eye.
他拯救不了你
He's not your deliverance.
那你覺得你能
You think you are?
指望精靈
Elf?
我要替祖先說句話
I'll say this for our ancestors.
敵人并沒有殺他們啊
They lived!
只要團結一致 我們就能活下來
Together, we can survive this.
如果跟我走 我們必定會活下來
Follow me, and together, we will!
來吧 都跟我走 來吧
Come on. Let's go. Come on. Follow me. Come on!
來吧
-Come on!
跟我走
Follow me!
希奧
Theo!
這是我們的好機會 好時機 快來
It's our chance. It's our time. Come on.
跟我一起走 來吧 小伙子 跟我來
With me. Come on, lad. Follow me, lad.
能幫我一把嗎
Right. Okay. Give me a hand, will ya?
再高點…
Higher. Higher!
小伙子們 這一輪足夠了
-Enough for that run, lads.
現在往外運吧
Ferry it out now.
-父親 -伊熙爾杜
-Father. -Isildur.
我們能聊聊嗎
May we speak?
為什么沒有選我進遠征軍
Why wasn't I chosen for the expedition?
-我以為你要去西部 -不去了
-Thought you were going west. -Not anymore.
我要先做點 配得上努門諾爾人做的事
Not till I've done something worthy of Númenor.
那是什么事呢 用你自己的話來說
And what is that? In your words.
我描述不出來
I don't have words for it.
所以我才非常努力地尋找
That's why I'm trying so hard to find it.
所以我才來尋求您的幫助
Why I'm asking for your help.
我倒是希望能幫你
Wish I could provide it.
但志愿者的數量 遠遠超出了我們能容納的范圍
But we've far more volunteers than we could ever hope to accommodate.
這城市有一半的人想要登上那些船
Half the city wants a spot on those boats.
把我塞進隊列的前排
Slip me to the front of the line.
你有什么資格
What are your qualifications?
-“資格”  -你隸屬于海上衛隊嗎
-"Qualifications"? -Do you belong to the Sea Guard?
-你明知道我比水手厲害得多… -你隸屬于海上衛隊嗎
-You know I'm twice the sailor... -Do you belong to the Sea Guard?
女王衛隊呢 商人公會呢
What about the Queen's Guard? Merchant's Guild?
-看來有正式編制才是重點 -騎士公會呢
-This is about uniform. -Horseman's Guild?
你太扯了
You're being absurd.
你還在假裝 忠于這座島上的傳統的時候
While you were feigning fidelity to the traditions of this isle,
這些人已經在將傳統發揚光大了
these men were living them.
他們想盡辦法貢獻力量 志愿出征
Finding ways to contribute. To serve.
這些東西顯然你并不在乎
Something of which you evidently care little.
我在乎 而且我準備好出征了
I care. I'm ready to serve.
只有這件事能讓我感到自豪
Nothing would make me prouder.
但是你錯失了良機
But you had your chance.
而且你已經做出了選擇
And you made your choice.
讓努門諾爾人冒著生命之險
-Risk Númenorean lives
就為了一些骯臟的中洲南方人 和一個好戰的精靈
for some grimy Southlander and a warmongering Elf?
法拉宗國師  你為什么要讓我們的親人去送死
Consul Pharaz?n! Why are you sending our kinsmen off to die?
法拉宗
-Pharaz?n! Pharaz?n!
-法拉宗  -跟我來
-Pharaz?n! -Come with me.
請原諒我沒發消息 這周太難熬了
Forgive me for not sending word to you sooner. Been a trying week.
他為什么不阻止這一切
Why didn't he stop this?
-他忠于女王 不論對… -肯定是錯
-He's loyal to her. Rightly or... -Wrongly.
很多人和你感覺一樣 但這還不足以改變他的想法 但是…
There are many who feel as you do. Not enough to sway him yet, but
只有你可以去說服他 他會聽你的
given the right push... Then it must be you. He will listen to you.
我一開口說話 他就閉耳塞聽
When I speak, his ears close up.
那你就大點聲說
So speak louder.
中洲南方人
Oi, Southlander.
有人找你
You have visitors.
敵人接下來去哪里了
And where did the enemy head next?
我認為敵人繼續往南 朝著歐斯提力斯瞭望塔進軍
Further south, I should think. Towards the watchtower of Ostirith.
我去通知海上衛隊
I'll inform the Sea Guard.
非常感謝 哈爾布蘭德大人
My thanks, Lord Halbrand.
我敢肯定 等我們登陸后 你的民眾一定會發揮重要作用
I'm certain your fellowship will prove just as invaluable once we make landfall.
登陸
"Landfall?"
加拉德瑞爾告知我們 你希望團結你的人民
Galadriel informed us of your aspiration to unite your people.
她居然這樣說
Did she now?
我相信她絕非未加思考脫口而出
I trust she was not speaking in haste?
其實 我的本意是…
As a matter of fact, it was my intention...
我的同伴只是覺得肩上的任務很重
My companion is merely feeling the weight of his task.
但我毫不懷疑 到時候 他會盡自己的一份力量
I have no doubt, come time, he will do his part.
我已經為本次任務背書 希望他能如你所說
Given that I've staked my name upon it, I should hope so.
攝政女王 您父親請您去一趟塔里
Queen Regent, your father has requested your presence in the tower.
“加拉德瑞爾告知我們”
"Galadriel informed us."
怪不得當時 女王居然知道要去她父親床邊堵截我
I wondered how the queen knew to waylay me at her father's bedside.
沒曾想到你為了公會徽章背叛了我
It never occurred to me you'd hand me over for a guild crest.
我之前懇求你放過我 但你卻利用了我
You used me. After I all but begged you to let me be.
我剛剛說服努門諾爾派出五艘船
I have just convinced Númenor to send five ships
和五百人來幫助你的人民
and 500 men to aid your people
幫你加冕為王
and place a crown upon your head.
很多人可能會認為是你利用了我
Many might assume you used me.
麻煩另找別人去加冕吧
Find another head to crown.
我不喜歡這里
I don't like it here.
沒事的 迪莉 只是樹而已
Oh, it's okay, Dil. It's just the trees.
他們選這條路是失心瘋了嗎
What madness made them go this way?
石頭足路就應該被封起來
Rockfoot Pass must be blocked in.
天黑路難行 繼續前進
Won't get any easier in the dark. Keep movin'.
“天黑路難行”
"Easier in the dark."
是狼群
Wolves.
你為什么不告訴我到底發生了什么
Why don't you tell me what's really goin' on?
每年的這個時節 這些樹林從沒有這樣光禿禿過
These woods have never been this bare this time of year.
原因太顯而易見了
It's as plain as lip fungus.
都怪他 不是嗎 那個大家伙
He is responsible, isn't he? The big fella.
你希望我怎么做
What precisely do you expect me to do about it?
做你當初在營地就該做的事
What you ought to have done at the camp.
卸掉他們的推車輪子 丟下他們
-Take their wheels and leave them!
到底要怎么樣你才肯做
What's it gonna take?
非得有人變成寡婦
Make a widow of somebody?
或者孤兒嗎
Or an orphan?
大家都餓了
People are gettin' hungry.
跟緊了
Stay close.
這很奇怪…
Oh, this is very strange. Most peculiar.
非常奇怪…
Most peculiar.
-你們差點嚇死我了 -瑪爾娃
-You nearly caused my heart to burst. -Malva.
-我們看到腳印了 -在泥里
-We saw footprints. -In the mud.
請你們一個一個說
-Lots of 'em! -One at a time, please!
快跑
-Run!
快點 快跑
-Come on! Run!
諾瑞
Nori!
Nori! Nori!
諾瑞 快躲開
Nori, get away from there!
諾瑞
-Nori! Nori!
不要 它會咬到你的
No! It'll get you!
堅守陣地 安塔摩
Hold your ground, Ontamo.
讓你的父親感到驕傲
Make your father proud.
他們的擊打動作 像北荒原的巖石巨人一樣笨拙
Their strokes fall like the Stone-giants of the North Moors.
但是
And yet?
他們沒有對付這個敵人的經驗
They are untested against this foe.
或許精靈愿意提供一些指導
Perhaps the Elf would be willing to offer some instructions?
殺死奧克的方法有很多種
There are many ways to kill an Orc.
但對你們而言 我建議用簡潔有力的方法
But for you, I will keep it strong and simple.
猛刺 旋扭 拔出
Stab, twist, gut.
跟我比劃一下
Come at me.
看看誰能傷得了我
We will see who can score flesh.
有誰能打贏精靈 我會提拔他為…
Anyone that does, I will promote...
中尉
To lieutenant.
劍法的核心是平衡 而并非力量
Swordsmanship is about balance, rather than strength.
對戰要用你的雙腳 而不是雙臂
Fight with your feet. Not your arms.
那個精靈正在廣場上與一名士兵切磋
The Elf is fighting a soldier in the square.
腳不要站定
Don't plant roots.
要不斷移動
-Keep moving.
靠蠻力永遠無法戰勝奧克
Never trust brute force to best an Orc.
以謀略制勝往往是最容易的
It's often easiest to outmaneuver them.
干得好 中尉
Well done, Lieutenant.
我從來都不知道 鐵匠的助手能有這般功夫
Never known a smith's aide who could do that.
現在叫停這一切還為時不晚
It's not too late to stop this.
雖然權杖在你堂姐手中 但眾人追隨的領袖是你
Your cousin may hold the scepter, but it's you the people follow.
-在眾人的幫助下 你可以… -可以什么
-With their help you could... -Could what?
施加你的影響力
Assert your influence.
有的時候 年輕人的愚蠢足以把年長者氣哭
Sometimes the folly of youth is enough to make an old man weep.
試圖阻止戰爭算愚蠢嗎
Is it folly to try and stop a war?
逆流而上是愚蠢的
It's folly to kick against the current.
是這樣 潮水可能漲起來淹死人
You see, the tide may rise and drown a man,
也可能落潮把人卷入海里
or fall and sweep him out to sea.
控制潮水的訣竅 是要知道它接下來會朝哪個方向流動
The trick of mastering the current is to know which way it will turn next.
你曾單槍匹馬阻止了上一任國王
You all but single-handedly prevented our last king
把我們拖回老路
from dragging us back to the old ways.
別告訴我你現在無法 改變彌瑞爾的想法
Don't tell me you couldn't sway Míriel's mind now.
是什么讓你覺得 彌瑞爾和我的想法不一致
And what makes you think Míriel's mind and my own are not as one on this?
因為我父親寧可死 也不會接受精靈的命令
Because my father would sooner die than take orders from an Elf.
“精靈的命令”
"Orders from an Elf"?
等這一切結束之后 將會是精靈們聽從我們的號令
When all this has ended, Elves will take orders from us.
只要我堂姐愿意 她可以為加拉德瑞爾出戰
Now, my cousin can go to war for Galadriel if she wishes.
但我是為了努門諾爾而戰
I go to war for Númenor.
這怎么會是為努門諾爾而戰呢
How could this be for Númenor?
你都白學了嗎
Have you learned nothing?
很快 我們將拯救中洲的下等人
Soon, we will save the low men of Middle-earth,
抬高他們的地位 給他們期待已久的國王
lift them up, and give them the king they've long awaited.
這個國王將永遠欠我們的債
A king who will be forever in our debt.
看你現在能不能想明白 這會對我們有什么好處
Now, contemplate, if you can, how that might benefit us.
礦石 森林 貿易 貢品…
Ores, forests, trades, tribute...
所以我可不敢 阻止這場戰爭 給我千金都不換
I wouldn't dare stop that. Not for all the salt in the sea.
你也不應該阻止這場戰爭
And neither should you.
這座王國
The kingdom!
-這座王國處于危險之中 我必須… -危險已經過去了 父親
-The kingdom is in danger. I must... -The danger has passed, Father.
我們正在做 您一直認為我們必須做的事情
We are doing now what you always believed we must.
我們正在恢復與精靈的關系
We're restoring our connection with the Elves.
我要去中洲
I'm going to Middle-earth.
彌瑞爾
Míriel?
我在呢 父親
Yes, Father.
是我
It's me.
別去中洲
Don't go to Middle-earth.
在那里 等待你的將是…
All that awaits you there is...
是什么 父親 等待我的將是什么
What, Father? What awaits me?
黑暗
Darkness.
你敢信嗎
Can you believe it?
大家都在說你剛才做的事
Everyone's talkin' about what you did.
從來沒有見過他們 這樣滿心喜歡一個外族人
Never seen 'em take a shine to an outsider like this before.
我給你帶了一些蜂蠟
Brought you some beeswax.
在你那大爪子上涂一點就沒那么疼了
Slather some on that paw, should help with the tenderness.
嘿
Hey.
住手 求你了
Stop. Please.
敬我們兩個偉大種族之間的長久聯盟
To an enduring union between our two great peoples,
卡扎德人和諾多族
Khazad and Noldor.
-敬聯盟 -敬聯盟
-To the union. -To the union.
在我們開懷暢飲之前
Before our wines ascend,
都林大人 我想贊揚你
Lord Durin, I should like to commend you.
卡扎督姆一向被稱為 矮人王國中最安靜的一個
Khazad-d?m has been called the quietest of Dwarven kingdoms,
但是最近幾個月 據說你們的熔爐在燃燒
but in recent months, your furnaces are said to be burning
火光亮得都快趕上奧力本尊的眼睛了
as bright as the eyes of Aul? himself.
而且你們的礦井鉆得越來越深
Your mines delving ever deeper.
這股新的活力您認為出自哪里呢
To what do you credit this new invigoration?
同樣的話我也想問林頓
I might ask the same of Lindon.
用船送走精靈戰士 擴建城市
Shipping off its warriors, expandin' its cities.
對精靈來說有點突然 不是嗎
Bit sudden for Elves, no?
你們每做一個決定 通常都要花他個好幾年…
Typically takes you people weeks just to decide to take a sh...
請允許我…
If I may...
對于我們精靈而言 時間流逝得很慢
The hand of time crawls so slowly for our kind.
我們經常會把 多年的辛苦努力視為短暫的付出
We often overlook the years of effort we perceive as taking but a moment.
希望我們這樣不會冒犯到我們的客人
In so doing, I would not wish to offend our guest.
如果能被一個真誠的提問所冒犯
I would think our Dwarven friend far too stout of heart
那這位矮人朋友未免也太頑固了
to be offended by an honest inquiry.
我有個真誠的問題想問你
I have an honest inquiry for you.
你從哪里弄來的這張桌子
From where did you procure the table?
你為什么這么問
Why do you ask?
這種石頭只分布在一定的深度
This stone grows only at certain depths.
特別稀少 以至于 我們的共鳴者很少能找到礦床
So rarely do our resonators locate a deposit.
我們將每一塊這種石頭 都視為珍貴的禮物
We consider each to be a precious gift.
把它留著用于最神圣的目的
We reserve its use for the most sacred purposes.
用來建造紀念碑或墳墓
Monuments or tombs,
紀念我們尊敬的逝者
to our honored dead.
請原諒我們的褻瀆 都林大人
Please forgive our sacrilege, Lord Durin.
我們一定會讓你 把它帶回家 好讓它得到應有的尊重
We shall have to send it home with you, so it can be treated with proper respect.
很高興知道 精靈當中還是存在些許榮譽感的
It's good to know there's still some honor left among the Elves.
陛下
Your Grace.
那么 敬我們兩族人民的聯盟
To the union of our two peoples, then.
敬聯盟
To the union.
你對這個矮人的忠誠令人欽佩
Your loyalty to the Dwarf is admirable.
理應這樣忠誠待友
Loyalty to a friend ought to be expected.
不論種族
Regardless of his race.
就憑這個 你就可以向國王撒謊嗎
Does it justify lying to your king?
至高王 我想知道 一直在對我撒謊的是不是您
I wonder, High King, if it is in fact you who has been lying to me.
我帶著友誼的提議 去了卡扎督姆 但事實上
I went to Khazad-d?m with a proposal of friendship, but in truth,
你卻在尋求 更看得見摸得著的東西 不是嗎
you sought something far more tangible, didn't you?
你熟悉 《希斯艾格利爾山根之歌》嗎
Are you familiar with The Song of the Roots of Hithaeglir?
請復述給我聽
-Recount it for me, please.
這是個鮮為人知的傳說 大多數人認為它是杜撰的
An obscure legend regarded by most to be a apocryphal.
復述一遍 埃爾隆德佩瑞蒂爾（“半精靈”）
Recount it, Elrond Peredhel.
這首歌講述了一場戰斗
It speaks of a battle,
在迷霧山脈高聳的山峰之間
high among the peaks of the Misty Mountains.
戰斗并非因榮耀 或使命而起 而是因為一棵樹
Not over honor or duty. But over a tree.
有些人稱這棵樹里 藏著最后一顆丟失的精靈寶鉆
Within which some claim was hidden the last of the lost Silmarils.
戰斗的一方是一位精靈戰士
On one side, fought an Elven warrior,
心如曼威般純潔
with a heart as pure as Manw?,
為了保護這棵樹 他將所有的光都傾注其中
who poured all of his light into the tree to protect it.
戰斗的另一方是魔茍斯的一個炎魔
-On the other, a Balrog of Morgoth,
把他所有的仇恨 都傳導到這棵樹上 以求將其摧毀
who channeled all his hatred into the tree to destroy it.
在他們無休止的決斗中 閃電擊中了這棵樹…
Amidst their duel unending, lightning ensnared the tree...
使他們的對抗造就了一股力量…
Forging of their conflict, a power...
這股力量如善良一般純凈而輕盈
A power as pure and light as good.
又像邪惡一樣堅強不屈
As strong and unyielding as evil.
他們說這股力量從樹根滲入大山深處
They say it seeped down the roots into the mountain depths,
幾個世紀以來 它一直在等待
where for centuries now, it has waited.
都林說對了
Durin was right.
那你就是承認矮人確實找到了它
Then you admit the Dwarves did find it.
那種礦石蘊含著丟失的精靈寶鉆之光
The ore containing the light of the lost Silmaril.
我只承認這一點
I admit only this.
我答應過都林永遠不會 泄露他子民的秘密
I promised Durin never to reveal his people's secrets.
如果說 信守對他子民的承諾
And what if keeping your promise to his people
意味著你的同胞就要厄運難逃呢
meant ensuring the doom of your own?
我們第一次注意到這種情況 剛好在加拉德瑞爾回來之前
We first took notice of it just prior to Galadriel's return.
當時我們希望通過把她送走
We hoped that by sending her away,
抹去戰爭最后的痕跡
and so bringing an end to the last vestiges of war,
從而就此阻止樹的枯萎
we might arrest the decay.
但盡管我們竭盡全力
But despite our every effort,
枯萎還是加速了
our decline has only quickened.
這棵樹表面上的枯萎反映了它
The blight upon this tree is but an outer manifestation
內在的實質
of an inner reality.
靈族之光
That the light of the Eldar,
也就是我們的光 正在消逝
our light, is fading.
還有誰知道這件事
Who else knows about this?
只有極少數
Precious few.
我再問最后一次
I ask again, and for the last time,
矮人是不是找到了那種礦石
did the Dwarves find the ore or not?
我向都林發過誓
I swore an oath to Durin.
對有些人來說 如今發誓可能并沒有多大意義了
To some, that may now hold little weight.
但在我看來
But in my esteem,
正是誓言才讓 我們的靈魂緊緊連接在一起
it is by such things our very souls are bound.
我不打算僅僅為了希望而違背誓言
I do not intend to let mine slip away on the basis of mere hope.
希望從來都不是微不足道的 埃爾隆德…
Hope is never mere, Elrond...
即便希望很渺茫
even when it is meager.
當所有其他感官都睡著了
When all other senses sleep,
希望之眼會率先醒來 最后一個閉上
the eye of hope is first to awaken, last to shut.
如果精靈現在放棄中洲
If the Elves abandon Middle-earth now,
黑暗大軍將會在中洲大地上橫行
the armies of darkness will march over the face of the earth.
那將會是末日
It will be the end,
不僅是我們精靈族的末日 還是所有種族的末日
not just of our people, but all peoples.
如果能防止這種情況發生的希望
If the hope of preventing that is not reason enough
還不足以讓你重新考慮你的誓言
to make you reconsider your oath,
那你不妨再找一條出路
I suggest you find another.
由諸神之手創造
What was the land immortal hands
從隔離之海中升起的那地是何地
Rose up from Sundering Sea?
恩賜之地 星引之地
-Land of the gift, land of the star
將永遠閃耀
To shine eternally?
那是努門諾爾 美麗的努門諾爾
'Twas Númenor Fair Númenor
明亮之島充滿了恩惠優雅…
Bright isle filled with grace...
我就說不會有危險的
I said it won't be dangerous.
我打賭等我下船的時候 一切就都結束了
I wager it'll all be over by the time I get off the boat.
但不要告訴我父親
Just don't tell my father.
他逢人便夸 未來的女婿是個戰爭英雄
He keeps crowing to everyone with ears, his future son-in-law's a war hero.
歌唱吧 來吧 唱起來
Sing! Come on, sing.
你還記得歌詞吧
You remember the words, don't you?
聽你鬼哭狼嚎了一宿 恐怕歌詞我永遠都忘不掉了
After hearing you squawk them all night, I fear I'll never forget them.
也許伊熙爾杜會和你一起唱
Perhaps Isildur will sing with you.
這就有意思了
This should be interesting.
讓我們偉大的島嶼永遠屹立 讓我們的劍戰勝死亡
Make our great land to ever stand Our swords to conquer death
-答案是不行 -我還什么都沒說呢
-The answer's no. -I haven't said anything yet.
我認識你15年了
I've known you 15 years.
你真覺得 我不知道你來是要說什么嗎
You think I don't know what you're here to say?
-其實是16年 但我的意思是… -安塔摩
-It's actually 16, but I mean... -Ontamo.
好吧 我來是要說什么
Right. What have I come to say?
你要非常誠懇地道歉 當然了 安塔摩肯定會
A fairly lavish apology, which Ontamo, of course,
立馬接受道歉 但我可不會
would've accepted instantly, but I wouldn't have.
你知道為什么嗎
And do you know why?
你愿意道歉 只是因為你覺得現在我升職了
You're only apologizing because you think now that I've been promoted,
我可以帶你參加遠征軍
I can get you on the expedition.
-可以帶我嗎  -我就說吧
-Can you? -Right.
我只想說 我不會馬上接受你的道歉
I'd just like to say, I wouldn't have accepted instantly.
-我很高興你道歉了 -他沒有
-But I am glad that you apologized. -No, he didn't.
我道歉了
I did!
但我很樂意再道一次 對不起 是我挑起了那次爭執
But I'll gladly do it again. I'm sorry I started the fight.
現在請帶上我吧
Now please bring me with you.
不行
No.
我到底要怎么做才能彌補過錯
What'll it take to make this right?
好吧 你可以隨便打我一拳
Fine, you get a free hit.
下巴或肚子都可以 任打一拳
Jaw, gut, your choice. One hit.
三
Three.
二
Uh, two.
其實…
-Actually...
我感覺被打了三拳
That felt like three.
好了 那你們能帶我上船嗎
So, you'll bring me on the ship?
伊熙爾杜 你是我相處最久的朋友
Isildur, you're my oldest friend.
說實話 現在你可能 仍然是我最好的朋友 但是…
And if you want to know the truth, you're probably still my best, but...
-怎么了  -安塔摩 拜托了
-What? -Ontamo, please.
不行 憑良心 我不能為你背書
I can't, in good conscience, stake my name
推薦你履行一項你可能會放棄的職責
recommending you for a duty that you might well decide to abandon.
這次會不一樣的
-It'll be different this time. -Hmm.
我也希望有一天會不一樣
One day, I hope it will be.
我也希望有一天你能找到
One day, I hope you find something
愿意為之犧牲一切的東西
that you would be willing to sacrifice anything for.
我會替你照顧貝雷克的 我保證
I'll take care of Berek for you. I promise.
貝雷克要去
Berek's going?
馴馬師把他招來了
The horsemaster recruited him.
抱歉 伊熙爾杜 大海永遠是正確的
Sorry, Isil. The sea is always right.
你是要偷渡出去嗎
Are you stowing away?
你是要把這艘船燒掉嗎
Are you about to burn the boat?
馬上離開這里 我不會告訴任何人我看到過你
Get out of here this moment. I won't let anyone know I saw you.
-把燈遞給我 -別過來
-Hand me the lantern. -Don't.
把燈給我
-Give it.
把大家召集起來 快點
Gather every hand. Hurry!
把他們救上來 快點
Get them out. Quickly.
把他們救上來  伊熙爾杜
Get them out! Isildur?
伊熙爾杜
Isildur?
怎么回事
What happened?
他剛才在一艘漁船上 一定是有酒桶爆炸了
He was in a fishing boat. A cask must've gone up.
酒桶
-A cask?
他救了我的命
He saved my life.
他本可以丟下我 但他卻救了我的命
He could've just left, but he saved my life.
船長
Captain!
我們有理由懷疑 是一個經過的強盜所為
We have reason to suspect a passing brigand,
但暫時還沒有確認其身份
but we've yet to identify him.
我們很走運 其他的船只沒有被燒毀
We're fortunate we didn't lose the rest of the ships as well.
這顯然是意圖激起你的疑慮 攝政女王
This was clearly an attempt to kindle your doubts, Queen Regent.
-別上當 -我不敢茍同精靈的看法
-Do not let it. -I'm forced to disagree with the Elf.
也許我們確實操之過急了
Perhaps we did act in haste.
王國應該被帶領 而不是被拖拽著走
A kingdom should be led. Not dragged.
我建議推遲出航
I recommend we delay the voyage
先為您的事業贏得更多的民心
until we've had time enough to win more hearts to your cause.
敵人一天比一天強大 也許每猶豫一小時 敵人就更強大些
Our enemy grows stronger every day. Perhaps every hour we hesitate.
要記住你為什么 選擇了這條路 記住你的信念
Remember why you chose this path. Remember your faith.
你覺得我能忘記嗎
Do you think I could forget?
我們還有三艘船 而且還有你父親的祝福
We still have three ships. And your father's blessing.
哈爾布蘭德大人呢
What of Lord Halbrand?
他在等待我們啟航
He awaits our departure.
可不是嘛
I'm sure he does.
我要不要讓海上衛隊先撤下來
Shall I tell the Sea Guard to stand down?
天一亮就重新召開會議 做最后的決定
This council will reconvene at first light to make a final decision.
要確保哈爾布蘭德大人參會
See to it Lord Halbrand attends.
你能確定的是什么
What have you been able to ascertain?
埃爾隆德 原諒我
Elrond, forgive me.
原諒你
Forgive you?
原諒我沒有早點告訴你
That I did not tell you sooner.
原來你早就知道的
You knew.
從一開始 我就求至高王把我們的秘密告訴你
I begged him to allow you into our confidence from the start,
但他不同意這樣做
but the High King forbade it.
這個秘銀…
And this... this mithril...
這是我們唯一的救贖嗎
It is our only salvation?
埃爾隆德 我在各種惡劣條件下都測試過它
Elrond, I have tested it under every duress.
任何事物都無法削弱它的光
Nothing diminishes its light.
我們相信 如果能快速獲得大量秘銀
We believe if we can secure vast quantities of it quickly,
多到足以再次 讓每一個精靈浸潤在維拉之光中…
enough to saturate every last Elf in the light of the Valar once more...
那么 是的
Then, yes.
是的 它是我們唯一的救贖
Yes. It very well could be.
抱歉
I am sorry.
至高王騙了我
That the High King deceived me?
還是說 我們精靈 注定要滅亡 除非我違背誓言
Or that now our people are doomed unless I break an oath?
背叛朋友
And betray a friend?
埃爾隆德 你父親啟航的那個晚上我在場
I was there, Elrond, the night your father set sail.
他一介凡人 相信自己可以說服眾神
A mortal man, who believed he could convince the very Gods
讓他們參戰幫助我們
to come to war in our aid.
我聽到你媽媽懇求他不要去
I heard your mother pleading with him not to go,
要求他 哀求他別去 問他為什么非他不可
asking him, imploring him, why, why must it be him?
你知道你父親說了什么嗎
And do you know what he said?
他說因為他是 唯一一個能做這件事的人
Because he was the only one who could do it.
我錯了 不應該利用你
I was wrong to use you.
對此 我很抱歉
For that, I'm sorry.
明天 女王會傳喚你覲見
Tomorrow, the queen will call you to audience.
你在會面上的態度 很可能會決定這次任務的成敗
Your voice at that meeting may well decide whether this mission stands or falls.
-幫幫我 -我想我已經幫你夠多了
-Help me. -I think I've helped you quite enough.
那就幫幫你自己
Then help yourself.
別再和我內斗了 跟我一起與敵人戰斗
Stop fighting me, and together, let us fight them.
不久前 我這類人卻還在與敵人為伍
Not so long ago, men like me were fighting alongside them.
但那是你的同胞 并不包括你
Men like you. Not you, yourself.
你錯了
You're wrong.
你不知道 我在坐上那艘木筏之前做了什么
You don't know what I did before I ended up on that raft.
你不知道我是怎么活下來的
You don't know how I survived.
我們所有人是如何得以幸存的
How we all survived.
如果被這些人發現 他們會把我趕出去
And when these people discover it, they will cast me out.
你也一樣
So will you.
有時候要找到光 我們必須先觸及黑暗
Sometimes to find the light, we must first touch the darkness.
你對黑暗了解多少
What do you know of darkness?
加拉德瑞爾 那把短劍是誰的
Whose dagger was it, Galadriel?
你失去的是誰
Who is it you lost?
我哥哥
My brother.
他出什么事了
What happened to him?
他被殺害了
He was killed.
在一個充斥著黑暗和絕望的地方
In a place of darkness and despair.
被索隆的仆從所殺 這樣你滿意了吧
By servants of Sauron. Is that enough for you?
所以這是為了復仇
So this is about vengeance?
區區復仇遠遠無法讓我滿足
One cannot satisfy thirst by drinking seawater.
那到底是為了什么  你為什么要一直戰斗
Then what is it? Why do you keep fighting?
你是在要我去一個 我發誓永遠不會回去的地方
You are asking me to go to the one place that I swore never to return.
所以起碼你可以告訴我為什么
The least you can do is tell me why.
你為什么要一直戰斗
Why do you keep fighting?
因為我停不下來
Because I cannot stop.
我領導的軍隊對我倒戈相向
The company I led mutinied against me.
我最親密的朋友 與至高王密謀將我流放
My closest friend conspired with the king to exile me.
我相信他們每個人之所以這樣做…
And each of them acted as they did...
是因為他們再也無法將我…
Because I believe they could no longer distinguish me...
與我正在抗爭的邪惡區分開來
from the evil I was fighting.
我很遺憾
I'm sorry.
你哥哥的犧牲
For your brother.
以及所有這一切
For all of it.
我替你感到難過
I'm sorry.
你的悲傷無法減輕我的痛苦
Your sorrow cannot ease my pain.
屈尊當個鐵匠也不會減輕你的痛苦
And nor will a hammer and tongs ease yours.
你在這里不會找到內心的平靜
There is no peace to be found for you here.
我也找不到
And nor for me.
持久的平靜在這里無處可尋
No lasting peace in any path,
只能在隔離之海的對岸覓得
but that which lies across the sea.
我已經戰斗了幾個世紀 試圖得到我內心的平靜
I have fought for centuries, seeking to earn mine.
你也得這樣做才能獲得平靜
This is how you earn yours.
這一天我已經等待很久了
Long have I awaited this day.
等待您的同類終將歸來的這天
The day your kind would return at last,
把我們從淤泥和污穢中拯救出來
lift us up from the muck and the filth,
讓我們在您身邊找回自己的位置
to take our rightful place at your side.
我向您保證我對您的忠誠至死不渝
I pledge my undying service to you.
我向索隆宣誓效忠
I pledge my loyalty to Sauron.
您是索隆吧
You are Sauron, are you not?
嘿…等等…
Hey, hey... Wait...
那無論您是誰 我都效忠于您
I'll serve you, then. Whoever you are.
只有雙手沾血才能證明忠誠
Only blood can bind.
沃德雷格
Waldreg?
沃德雷格…
Waldreg...
沃德雷格 不要
Waldreg, no.
不要…
No.
-No.
不要
No!
下次瞄高一點
Lift your aim next time.
別那么害怕弓弦
And don't be so afraid of the string.
何苦要費心教我
Why bother trying to teach me?
因為我花了兩百多年
Because it took me over 200 years
才有了今晚站在這里的勇氣
to develop the bravery that's keeping me standing here tonight.
而你僅僅14歲就有這樣的勇氣了
You found it in only 14.
戰斗中我們需要這種勇氣
And we're going to need it in the fight to come.
在我一生中 你們精靈一直監視著我們
All my life, your kind has watched us.
清點我們說過的每一句悄悄話
Counting every whisper.
留意每一把過于鋒利的餐刀
Every kitchen knife too sharp.
我們都快要被埋在這座瞭望塔里了
We're all about to be buried in this tower.
何苦還要跟我們一起陪葬呢
So why be buried with us?
因為在清點悄悄話和餐刀的時候
Because in counting the whispers and the knives,
我開始了解在它們背后的活生生的人
I've come to know the voices and the hands of those behind them.
我們的人已經走了一半
Half of us just left.
但還有一半選擇了留下
But half stayed.
包括你
Including you.
所以 瞄高一點
So lift your aim.
有件事你不知道
There's something you don't know.
我以前見過這個
I've seen this before.
這是一把鑰匙
It is a key.
敵人用一些失傳的手藝所制 用來奴役你的祖先
Conjured by some forgotten craft of the enemy, to enslave your ancestors.
是什么的鑰匙
A key to what?
我不知道
I do not know.
敵方指揮官說過要成為神
The enemy commander spoke of becoming a god.
要在這些土地上給奧克一個家
Of giving the Orcs a home in these lands.
但不管他有什么陰謀 有一點是肯定的
But whatever his design, this much is certain.
敵人知道你兒子 有他需要用來啟動計劃的東西
Our enemy knows your son has what he needs to enact it.
要多久
How long?
幾天吧
Days.
也可能是幾個小時
Maybe hours.
我們會活下來的 布隆溫
We can survive this, Bronwyn.
有辦法
There is a way.
肯定有
There must be.
的確有一個辦法
There is one.
不行 向敵人低頭 意味著你就奪走了一切
No! Bow to the enemy, and you take away everything.
奪走了子孫后代的一切
From your son, and his sons after him.
你們祖輩辛勤勞作了 整整一個紀元 才贏回了自己的品性
Your people have worked an entire age to earn back their virtue.
僅僅因為一時的絕望 你就要讓它前功盡棄嗎
Would you undo it all in just one moment of despair?
肯定還有別的辦法
There must be another way.
那說出來聽聽 我求你了
Name it. I beg you.
我沒說錯吧
See?
你們盯著我們是對的
You were right to watch us.
因為我們注定要墮入黑暗
Because we are destined for the darkness.
這就是我們的生存方式
It's how we survive.
也許我們就是這樣的人
Perhaps it's who we are.
永遠將會是這樣的人
Who we will always be.
處于風險之中的 可遠遠不只有我們的性命
There's far more at stake here than just our lives.
當年魔茍斯開戰 整個貝烈瑞安德都淪陷了
When Morgoth was at war, whole continents sank.
有誰能說得出 這次會引發什么樣的可怕后果
Who is to say what horrors this might unleash,
就應該讓敵人得逞嗎
should our enemy obtain it?
我們有什么力量去阻止他
What power do we have to stop him?
看看周圍 已經完蛋了
Look around. It's over.
-還沒有 -很快就要完蛋了
-Not yet. -Soon enough.
等敵人向我們進軍時 這座瞭望塔就會倒下
And when they march upon us, this tower will fall.
戰斗
Nampat!
剛才你是瞎編的 不是嗎
You made it up, didn't you?
迪莎多年來 一直想要一張新桌子 所以…
Disa's been wanting a new table for years, so...
快得了 這桌子哪有那么重
Ah, come on, it's not that heavy.
讓我感到負擔沉重的 不是這張桌子的重量
It is not the weight of the table that burdens me.
那你為什么不說出來
So why don't you come out with it?
因為負擔拿出來分擔 有可能會減半 也有可能會加倍
Because a burden shared may either be halved or doubled.
取決于聽話人的同理心
-Depending on the heart that receives it.
奧力的胡子啊 你別繞彎子了
Aul?'s beard! Enough with the quail sauce.
大大方方說 不用避諱
Give me the meat, and give it to me raw.
我沒有對你說實話 都林
I have not been truthful with you, Durin.
我來卡扎督姆 并非為了友誼 而是有目的而來
I did not come to Khazad-d?m for friendship, but ambition.
但我之前并不知情
I did not know it.
我此行的任務是尋找秘銀
But I came for mithril.
為什么
Why?
如果沒有秘銀
Without it,
我們精靈族要么 得在春天離開這些海岸 要么滅亡
my kind must either abandon these shores by spring, or perish.
滅亡
Perish?
怎么滅亡
Perish how?
我們不朽的靈魂將化為烏有
Our immortal souls will dwindle into nothing,
慢慢衰減耗盡
slowly diminishing,
直到我們變成虛影
until we are but shadows,
被時間的潮汐沖走
swept away by the tides of time.
永不復生
Forever.
所以整個精靈族的命運 都掌握在我手中
So the fate of the entire Elven race is in my hands?
看起來是這樣的
So it would appear.
再說一次
Say that again.
整個精靈族的命運都掌握在你手中
The fate of the entire Elven race is in your hands.
誰的手中
Whose hands?
你的
Yours.
收起你那軟弱的玻璃心 我們走吧
Fetch your feathery shirts. Let's start walking.
-都林… -先別急著謝我
-Durin... -Don't thank me yet.
等我們想辦法 說服我父親之后 再謝我吧
Thank me after we find a way to convince my father.
現在我們可以動身了嗎
Now can we please get moving?
回去的路很長
It's a long journey back.
這些陽光都開始讓我胃不舒服了
And all this sunlight is startin' to give me a sour stomach.
有個條件 你告訴迪莎這張桌子是我給的
Under one condition. Tell Disa the table's from me.
你別得寸進尺 精靈
Don't push your luck, Elf.
哈爾布蘭德大人 攝政女王召見您
Lord Halbrand, the Queen Regent summons you.
看看是誰又靠他爹弄到了一個位置啊
Look whose father secured him a post. Again.
我是自己爭取到的 和你一樣
I earned mine. Same as you.
士兵
Soldier.
去向馴馬師報道
Report to the horsemaster.
我以為我是騎兵
Thought I was in cavalry.
你的確是
You are.
負責清掃馬廄
Stable sweep.
士兵們
Soldiers!
解開繩索
Clear the lines!
揚帆遠航
Square the sail!
我們朝東北方向行進
We head nor'-east.
前往中洲
For Middle-earth.
耶
Yes!
太陽正在落下
The sun is fast falling
落在森巖的樹林后方
Beneath trees of stone
塔中之光
The light in the tower
不再是家鄉
No longer my home
過去燈火朦朧
Past eyes of pale fire
黑沙做我的睡床
Black sand for my bed
我用所知的一切
I trade all I've known
換取未知的未來
For the unknown ahead
呼喚我 遙遠之地 請呼喚我
Call to me Call to me lands far away
因為我現在 必須在這流浪的日子里游蕩
For I must now wander this wandering day
我必須游蕩
Away I must wander
在這流浪的日子里
This wandering day
我缺水
Of drink I have little
我少食
And food I have less
我的力量告訴我不行 但是這條路要求我踏足
My strength tells me no But the path demands yes
我雙腿很短 而道阻且長
My legs are so short And the way is so long
無法休息 何談舒適
I've no rest nor comfort
無所慰藉 唯有歌聲
No comfort, but song
為我歌唱 遙遠之地 請為我歌唱
Sing to me, sing to me Lands far away
請起身指引我度過這流浪的日子
Oh, rise up and guide me This wandering day
請答應要找到我
Please promise to find me
在這流浪的日子里
This wandering day
最終 他們的答案來了
At last comes their answer
穿過寒冷和霜凍
Through cold and through frost
并非所有的流浪者都身陷迷途
That not all who wonder or wander are lost
不論悲傷
No matter the sorrow
不計成本
No matter the cost
并非所有的流浪者都身陷迷途
That not all who wonder Or wander are... Lost
字幕翻譯：腐哥
創意監督 羅婷婷